When it comes to Yayin Nesach, S'tam
Yeinam, can we have protective seals so
that we're not concerned somebody touched it
or did something else to it? So
we ended off last time with a
discussion about in source the double seal,
which we saw in the Shulchan Aruch
Igros Moshe, the double seal is not
a din in the double seal, it's
more of a din in the effort
that is going to have to be
put in to actually taking it up.
We finished with in source 40 about
the same idea, Torech Rav, it's going
to be a lot, a lot of
work. Okay. Is there enough in let's
say I have a single seal that's
just like airplane food, you cannot get
it off. Correct, yes, so we're going
to talk about that, yeah, yeah. We're
going to talk about doing... it would
need something else. I mean the tin
foil and then that and then that
plastic thing. I mean the plastic is
nearly impossible. Correct, correct. It would still
need two. It would still need two
as long as, unless the one is
really, really, really amazing. It seems like
it would still, Rav Moshe would probably
say one. Could be that it's one.
Could be that it's one. So we'll
see in a little bit about on
this idea. So let's go to source
41. So when it comes to a
cork, okay? So when it comes to
a cork, if you look in source,
so again, most wine bottles today have
the cork and then they also have
some kind of aluminum foil, I don't
know the wines that I buy, some
of them have the twist off. Yeah,
yeah, yeah. So it's a corked bottle,
so to Howard's point, you would still
need the foil wrapping. So in source
41 he paskens the following: בקבוקים שלנו
שבקק של שעוה או מתכת מהודק ועל
יש כיסוי ניילון af she'eino mudpas הרי
הוא כשני חותמות. So again, you would
need two, but it would seem that
if the foil was already removed, potentially
it would be a problem. But if
you go to source... and you twist
off please? So we saw we said
last week with a twist-off lid, so
it's if you twist off that cap,
it's very, almost impossible for you to
put the cap, to reseal the cap
back to the ring. So that would
be a double, as long as so
there you probably would paskin one would
be enough because no way to get
it back. So okay. So if you
look in source 42, just to get
back to corks for a second. בקבוק
יין שבקק שם שאי אפשר לפותחו אלא
על ידי פותחן המקלקל את הפקק, the
way that you do it is that
you destroy the cork. Okay? I don't
know about how fancy people open their
wine bottles, but when I finish with
a corkscrew, that thing is not going
to have... probably seen the bottle at
that point. So he says that's chashuv
k'veis chosamos. He says that would be.
Since the normal way to remove it
is by pulling out with the corkscrew,
which would damage it, the intact cork
would be potentially that would be enough
to ensure that it's a double seal.
So he explains in the footnote. He
says in the footnote he quotes the
Sefer Yayin Malchos. I don't know who
the Sefer Yayin Malchos is, but he
quotes in the Sefer Yayin Malchos שקיבל
ושמע מרבותיו שם שהכל תלוי בטרחא, that
once again, that we're a little bit
nervous because sometimes you could remove a
cork without really destroying the cork. So
what's my concern? My concern is that
if it's not a lot of work
to take out the cork, then maybe
somebody took out the cork, drank some
of the wine, and then just put
the cork back in. I wouldn't know
when I came back. It looks like
they had just... yeah, but in my
limited experience, you can put the cork
back in, but you can't put it
in all the way. Correct, correct. So
he... Correct. If you use the corkscrew,
then it's got a hole in it.
You can see the hole in the
cork. Right, right, right. Right. So again,
I agree. He's quoting this what... but
if you look in the left side,
it's very interesting that he quotes in
the on the left side that this
would not be the same thing when
it comes to champagne, which is why?
Because it pops out, you're not going
to... Right, because the moment it's removed,
you can't get it back in. Okay,
good. Fine. So that's when it comes
to that's when it comes to corks.
So lema'aseh lema'aseh, how do we... here
I am in my... this is all
about what comes to a closed bottle.
Is there any way to keep an
open bottle of wine on my counter
knowing that there might be non-Jewish people
in my house, cleaning up in my
house, or somebody might be present who
might touch the wine? So there are
going to be a number of solutions.
Solution number one is going to be
just create your own double seal, meaning...
I'll figure it out. Take a bag,
wrap some tape around it, make some
fancy I don't know notes and you'll
know that if they ripped it apart,
they ripped it apart, so that would
be fine. If you look in source
43, says the Aruch Hashulchan in source
43 that if you fastened a cap
so tightly, צרירה בחזק פי השק מותר,
if you fastened the cap so tightly
that in order to remove that cap,
I would need some kind of tool.
If you need some kind of tool,
that's considered a chosum acher, דצרירה בעצמה
הוי חותם, and we're going to see
a little bit later, specifically when it
comes to workers, they're not going to
do something that would also threaten their
employment, which we'll get to. So he
explains that same thing, the Aruch Hashulchan
says, that if you fasten it really,
really, really tightly, so if I had
a bag and I tied it really
tight around this thing and the only
way to get the bag off was
to cut it with something, that would
be considered one way to get around
it. Fine. Next, if you go, oh
very interesting, go to source 44. I
don't know if you've ever seen these
in Eretz Yisroel, they have in Israel
these days a bottle cap that has
a numerical code. You see these? So
actually I've seen them, they have the
picture of them in the notes. It's
a cap you put on top and
just like a Shabbos code for your
house, it's a code to get into
the bottle of wine. Okay? Yeah. Get
off my Moscato, you know what I'm
saying? You gotta protect it. Now, so
the shaila is, and you see it
here in source 44, okay, so if
they can only remove it if they
knew the numerical code, now what, this
was created not for drinking, they were
really created to hopefully children don't get
into wine bottles. Right? ובשנים האחרונות נכנס
לשוק דבר הקרוי פקק עם קוד. So
there's bottles that now have a code
with it. And he says now, it's
interesting, it might actually depend on whether
it is a, this is just an
interesting thing, you can say what you
can disagree with either this, whether it's
a three-digit numerical code or a four-digit,
now not to get into Terumos u'Maaseros
yet for next zman, but in order
numerically for me to try all codes
with three digits, how long would it
take me? Very little time. It's not
a ton of time, I don't know.
So he says the following. Shoteh b'shichivah?
It says no. Well, an hour? It's
less than, no, five minutes. Not for
Rain Man. I'm saying like, why would
you need to be troubled? What? You
don't need to know the code for
the front door. The bottle caps say
Luchos, Imos, you know, it's like Shul.
So lemaiseh he says the following. So
he says פקק זה שיכול אדם להסגיר
את הבקבוק באופן שאף אחד לא ישתה
מן הבקבוק ויש לעיין אם נחשב הדבר
כבקבוק חתום אשר לא נחשש למגע יין
נסך. Okay, so now I have this
thing that let's say a guy comes
along and touches the bottle, moves the
bottle, but there's no way that it
affected the wine. So he says that
it seems that it should be okay.
Shulchan Aruch nakat l'dina כיצד היה חותם
בתוך חותם, so the Shulchan Aruch paskens
what is considered a double seal, שהחבית
בכלי שאינו מהודק כדרך שחוסמים כל אדם,
I close it regularly, and then I
put it with some kind of sealant,
that's chosum echad, הכלי מהודק וטוחנו מלמעלה,
if I close it and then I
sealed it, okay, so that's chosum b'toch
chosum. So he says לפי זה היה
מקום לומר שסגירת הפקק תחשב לחותם הראשון,
the bottle is one, and the code
is number two. That's what he holds,
that's what he says, I could make
an argument. The cap, even though it
looks at the same, the same thing,
the cap itself is one, doesn't have
to, as long as it goes on,
doesn't have to seal, and the code
is the seal. Because it's two steps.
Meaning you have to do, yeah, correct,
correct. Meaning step one is that it
has to be closed with something, I
don't have to seal it, I just
have to close it, and close it
with that I locked it, the way
that I locked it is the numerical
code. Fine. Then he says further, ולעניות
דעתי כיוון שעובד יכול לפתוח את הבקבוק
בלי שיורגש כלל. But what's the problem?
If I, do you ever see, remember
an old movie Sneakers? Anybody? Great movie.
Anyway, separate topic. But they crack the,
okay if I crack the code and
I open the bottle of wine, if
I crack your cork, it's not going
to look the same because I destroyed
it. But if I crack the code
and I drink wine and then I
re-lock the code, you're none the wiser.
So he says ולעניות דעתי כיוון שעובד
יכול לפתוח את הבקבוק בלי שיורגש כלל.
The fact though that I could open
it without really anybody noticing, שהרי אם
משאירו בביתו לבדו פחות מחצי שעה. He's
a very smart guy. He could... Instead
of worrying about the code, we should
worry about real things that are that
are impacting Klal Yisrael. How about the
sticker of the lock itself? Why? Why
can't you make a mark, a notation
on the bottle so you can see
if something was taken out? Wait one
second. That's that's a third seal. We're
assuming that the person here is not
having a tiny little sip and moving
on. How do you know that? First
of all, one second. I I go
over to the Go-Meyer house. So you
you left a bottle, you left it
with a marker. Your wife took a
little bit of wine. So later you're
gonna come be choshed that somebody, that's
impossible to know. But you're choshed it's
just me and my wife, but you're
saying there are workers in the house.
So now I leave, no what I'm
saying but I put a mark on
there so I know. Yeah, but you
could put you could I could add
I could put Dr Pepper in there.
I could fill it up with something.
Then you could take the marker and
move the mark. You'd see it, smell
it or taste it, you're going to
know. How, you could change your mark.
You don't know where your mark was.
That's what I'm saying. Right. I don't
know. I don't know. I'm out on
this with this one. I'm pushing back.
Clearly you're not a drinker. Yeah. Yeah.
We could tell, us drinkers. So he
says, but then he says the following,
he says in the in the third
paragraph at the end, לעניות דעתי לא
חששו בכך כגון דטירחא יתירה says three
digits I I don't think it's that
that's so strong. But then he says
the following. He quotes Rav Eliyahu Schlesinger.
Says נראה לעניות דעתי דאפשר לסמוך על
זה כחותם בתוך חותם, actually no, I
I think this is an excellent double
seal. Why? גם גלוי לפניו דקשה מאד
לפענח המספר. He's not going to try
and sit there and attempt to do
the lock. Why? שרוצה לגנוב מבעל הבית
ולעשות דבר נגד הסכמתו לא ישקיע זמן
רב עבור זה. Let's be honest, this
is going to take you at best
a thirty minutes. We're going to talk
soon what other criteria when for what's
called Yotzei Venichnas. Fine. But this guy's
not going to be doing this thing
and therefore he says I think it's
fine. If he really wanted to steal
with for you, it would be easier
just to go and look for money
in your house than to take some
of this wine. ומשום לשתות יין לא
ישקיע זמן לפתוח בקבוק ויעדיף לחפש כסף
אם באמת רוצה לגנוב מבעל הבית. If
he's a real thief, just go find
the the envelope of cash that they
keep in their drawer upstairs and everything
will be fine. So this is this
interesting idea about this this lock. About
the She'elos Uteshuvos forty five, מנעול עם
מספרים על בקבוק יין נחשב כחותם בתוך
חותם. יש מנעול היום עם מספרים kmo,
I'm sorry, bakbuk yayin. They have these
codes. Is that considered like a double
seal? Because it's a big tircha to
figure it out? Says Rav Nevenzahl, tircha
yes, והנחשב כחותם בתוך חותם. So if
you had an open bottle of wine
and you had this fancy-fancy code lock
thing, your wine would be fine and
you could continue to drink it. Okay.
So that's approach number two. If you
go in the Shulchan Aruch, just to
show you, we go to Siman Kuf
Lamed, okay, go to Kuf Lamed Beis.
Okay. Now, says the Shulchan Aruch, המפקיד
ביד עובד כוכבים, if you gave the
guy your bottle of wine, בחותם אחד
אסור בשתיה ומותר בהנאה, you can't drink
it but you can get benefit from
it. ושהניח לו קרן זוית. That's when
he sort of gave you a a
place to put it. And then the
Rema says the following. ויש שכתבו דבדיעבד
יש להתיר אפילו בחותם אחד. Says the
Rema, if one seal we would be
meikal if we needed to. ואין צריך
להכיר חותמו אם לא שראה שהחותם מקולקל
אסור. So says the Rema, potentially we
would be meikal bedieved with one with
one seal, potentially even lechatchila. Why? So
we saw earlier in קוף יוד חית
א. Yes, we should have it here.
Okay, you don't have to look at
this one, but in קוף יוד חית
א says the Shulchan Aruch, קוף יוד
חית א, hold on, it's a long
siman, it's a long sif here, but
the Shulchan Aruch here paskens that a
double seal was needed only if the
violation I am talking about is what
level? De-Oraisa. We today, what we're talking
about, is at best a de-rabanan. So
maybe I would not need to have
a a double seal. So in comes
the Aruch Hashulchan in source forty-six. So
we had a big Rema that said
this whole thing doesn't really apply. So
in comes the Aruch Hashulchan and he
says, hold on a second. כבר נתבאר
דבאיסור דאורייתא צריך שני חותמות. You're right,
I need double covering. If I want
to send you meat, I need to
have a double covering. It's got to
be double sealed. ואיסור דרבנן די בחותם
אחד. One's enough. ויין אף שמי דרבנן
החמירו בו כשל תורה. We might be
machmir. Why are we machmir? We said
earlier at the beginning of this month
why are we machmirin in Yayin Nesach?
Because of what it potentially could be
and it's Avoda Zara and things like
that. That's because we were choshesh for
chibash nisuch. But today he says, ולכן
הסכימו כמה מהגדולים דבזמן הזה לא שייך
זה. There is, if you're telling me
there was still Avoda Zara happening, so
then I have to be worried. There's
no Avoda Zara happening. So now we're
back to d'Rabbanan. I should have one
seal ככל איסורי דרבנן וכן יש להורות.
So says the Aruch Hashulchan, I really
could be meikel. Now, we are not,
we do not pasken this way lechatchila
like the Aruch Hashulchan. But in the
case of a person had, I don't
know, twenty-five wine bottles at home and
and there was a maid who went
through the housekeeper and it's a huge
hefsed merube case, we might be meikel
based on this Aruch Hashulchan that you
know there's room to be lenient. That
plus there's room to be lenient if
I'm worried that the goy, you know,
would never touch it because if they
knew they touched it they would lose
their job or whatever it is that
potentially there is what to be lenient
on. Okay. So lechatchila I can create
my own double seal, I can close
a cork really tight, or maybe even
in case of need I could be
meikel on this Aruch Hashulchan. Okay. The
final way is, well, let's say I
don't have any of those, but I
have something called yotzei v'nichnas. Now what's
yotzei v'nichnas? Says the Gemara the following.
Says the Mishna in Avoda Zara. You
have to understand there's certain criteria for
what it means yotzei v'nichnas. So says
the Mishna that if I want to
leave my produce of kosher wine in
a non-kosher winery, so he says the
following: התיר יינם של עובדי כוכבים ומזלות
ברשותו. And I want to put it
in his, in his reshus, and the
non-Jew's reshus, and that reshus, his property,
is pasuach l'reshus harabbim, and it opens,
everybody's there, ובעיר שיש בה עובדי כוכבים
וישראלים, that is mutar. That is mutar.
Why is that mutar? So Rashi says
דמירתת ליה עובד כוכבים ולא נגע. Why?
Because the goy, he's he's nervous, not
going to touch it. דאמר דלמא חזי
להנך ישראל דעברי ברשותא ומפסדינא. Maybe something's
going to happen, I'm going to lose
it, I'm not going to touch it.
Because a Jew might come in and
if he he comes in and I
might risk selling all, he's giving me
wine to sell, he knows that I
can't, I'm the middleman, the goy says.
If the if the Jew comes in
and sees him touching his wine, ah,
it's not going to be good for
my business, not going to give me
any more wine. Fine. Okay. Says the
Gemara, the Mishna continues, if עיר שכולה
עובדי כוכבים, then it's assur. However, ad
sheyeishev u'mshamer. However, as long as you
have a shomer, that's okay. And the
shomer doesn't need to be yoshev u'mshamer.
I don't need the guy to be
sitting there twenty-four seven, three-sixty-five watching and
watching watching it. אף על פי שיצא
ונכנס מותר. As long as I'm yotzei
v'nichnas. Okay. Now, the next Mishna in
Avoda Zara in source forty-eight X that
if I if I leave a non-Jew
in my store המניח עובד כוכבים בחנות
אף על פי שיצא ונכנס מותר. So
there's a non-Jew in my, I have
a non-Jewish worker, how am I worried
because he knows that I'm in and
out. ואם הודיעו שהוא מפליג כדי שישתום
ויסתום ויגוב. That he could do what?
So long as the we'll see Rabban
Gamliel in a second. But so long
as he's not going to be for
enough time that he's going to be
able to destroy it, take it out,
refill it. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר
כדי שיפתח את החבית ויגוב. He's got
to open the barrel, and he's got
to, you know, make the new lid,
and then he's got to, you know,
dry it and all these things. But
if I did leave for that long
enough time, says Rashi on the left
side, בשם רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אינו
נאסר אלא עד שישהה כדי שיפתח את
כל מגופת החבית. If I told him
listen, I'm heading out, I'm going to
be on a flight for the next
three hours, that's enough time to open
the barrel, to make a new lid,
to reseal it and everything, then it
would be assur. Okay. This is what
we call yotzei v'nichnas. In comes the
Tur as the Tur explains the following.
So the the Tur says, he quotes
the Rosh but yeah we're going to
see in a second. Now the Gemara
later Rava in the Gemara explains when
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל said this that's
only if there's another criteria. criterion and
that is the Jew the non-Jew can't
see the Jew coming. So like if
the store is open and there's just
one thoroughfare and he's at the end
of it I know he's coming then
that wouldn't work. But if there's many
ways to get in the house there's
many ways that he I the Jew
might just show up that's what רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל's going to be okay
with. So says the Tur using this
opinion of Rava. Says in the in
the bottom right side: מותר בשל זמן
רב שהוא ירא בכל פעם אתא יבא
ויראני We know this that's what we
just said. He's it's always muttar even
if it's a long time because he
doesn't know when the Jew is going
to be coming. ובלבד שלא יסגר הגוי
החנות that he can't be locked in
there by himself right? ולא ירחיק הקרון
והספינה and the sefinah can't be too
far away. במה דברים אמורים שיש שם
דרך עקלקלות where there's some kind of
you know angle שיכול לבא עליו פתאום
like the pasuk says in Malakhi the
ge'ulah will come yavo pit'om. Just comes
suddenly. That's the famous Zionist versus Chasidish
debate about Zionism. The debate about Zionism
is based on that pasuk in Malakhi
pit'om versus whatever. It's a good discussion.
So he says if I'm going to
the beit hamerchatz and I'm going to
go this roundabout way בענין שלא ידע
הגוי שהלך לבית המרחץ like Shaya just
said he doesn't know where I'm going.
אכן ירא בכל פעם אתא יבא And
he's always worried maybe he's going to
come. So number one is in addition
to all these other things he says
he can't be away for an extended
period of time and he also has
to make sure that he can come
in at any time. So you have
four criteria you have four criteria based
on this Tur. Number one the non-Jew
thinks the Jew could come at any
single time. If he thinks he's going
to come at any single time that's
number one and we're going to see
how many of these we need. Number
two when the Jew comes back he
opens the door and the door has
to be unlocked. If the door is
locked that's a problem. Number two. Number
three that the Jew is able to
show up you know suddenly right? That's
number three the first yotze venichnas not
locked and suddenly. And the fourth is
that I don't know how long he's
leaving for. Okay. The third you said
you're not going to know when he's
coming. If you have a store that
you're leaving with and you got cameras
whatever you can Ooh don't but we'll
get to the cameras in a second.
Ooh. Let's go to source 15 now.
Oh sorry go to the Shulchan Aruch
one second. קכט א and then we're
going to see about cameras. Okay so
the Shulchan Aruch says in קכט א
here המניח עובד כוכבים בחנותו if I
left a goi in my store ויצא
and I left או שהיה לו יין
בספינה or I have it on a
boat on a wagon והניחו עם עובד
כוכבים and I left it with a
goi והלך לבית הכנסת או לבית המרחץ
I went to shul or I went
to the bathhouse שעובד כוכבים עובר לו
חביות or he's traveling with it so
he says it's all going to be
okay אפילו שהה זמן רב even if
it's a long time דהוא ירא בכל
שעה אתא יבא ויראני maybe he's going
to come that's what we said שלא
נודע שסגר עובד כוכבים החנות it's not
locked שהרחיק or that people are unable
to see him. So again and he
continues on the following: according to the
Shulchan Aruch you need how many of
the four conditions? All. If you get
back and the door is locked or
if you get back and the guy
knew that you were coming all bets
are off. Doesn't work. Doesn't work. So
okay so today we have lots of
people in our homes people coming in
and out of our homes. So what
what what's the problem? So look at
source 50. Yeah if you look there's
a good Shach. It's not a big
Shach. If you go to the Shach
in קיח מב. קיח מב. So this
Shach here קיח מב that the Shach
says that we really limit this idea
of yotze venichnas to really be bedi'eved
only if the owner is actually out
for a long time. If he's out
for a long time longer than it
takes to seal everything then we would
need all of these like all these
conditions. If it's a very short time
we're probably not so concerned. If the
guy is actually yotze venichnas in and
out in and out in and out
like every five minutes you don't need
the door locked like if he says
I'm running to my car and he
locks the door and you get right
back we're not worried that in that
30 seconds even though he locked the
door he undid the lid and then
he put the lid back on and
he resealed it. He's not the Flash.
Okay. So now go to source 50.
Okay. So what about cameras? Cameras are
a big big topic in halachah especially
within the world of kashrut of mashgichim
things like that. So the Sefer Hashulchan
K'Hilchato paskens that if I am able
to install cameras in my kitchen then
maybe I could tell the cleaning help
you can't touch because I'm going to
check the cameras. So would that be
yotze venichnas? So he says: במקום שקשה
מאוד לשמור את היין if I can't
really watch the watch the wine, I
don't have a shomer there או עבור
זה עובד זר נכרי קבוע בבית של
אדם מוגבל או זקן and sometimes it
happens, a person has a caretaker, a
person has an aid. They're not they're
not there, you can't have a Jew
there the whole time. אפשר להתקין מצלמות
על היינות ולהודיע לנכרי you could put
a camera and you could say hey,
אפשר בכל רגע לראות I'm always going
to check אם נוגעים ביין שאסור להם
לנגוע ביין. Right? So that would seem
to be okay, that's basically a camera
is taking the place of a yotze
venichnas. Okay. Now, he quotes in the
footnote that potentially we would also seemingly
allow this: יש בזה שני צדי היתר.
האחד כיוצא ונכנס בלא זמן רב there's
no there's no zman rav anymore. I'm
always watching you. Therefore afillu l'chatchila and
also they're also always mifached tamid, they're
always worried. והשני שיש נקב בדלת שישראל
יכול לראות את הנכרי ואז היין אינו
נאסר. If there was a hole in
the door that they could always look
through, that would be the same thing.
So why would a camera be any
different? So we pasken like this, or
we pasken like this and we would
be okay with this. However, however, we
don't pasken like this for a lot
there's a big debate amongst kashrus organizations
about doing this for mashgichim. Could you
have a mashgiach that's in the I
don't need a mashgiach anymore, I have
a camera, and someone's always watching you.
So first of all, we're not going
to get into it now but we
can talk about, you know, different different
policies. What would be part of the
problem with that? Technical glitches. What else?
You're not really watching all the time.
But you have be'di'avad playback. Right. Now
you also isn't seeing everything anyway. Yeah,
yet the mashgiach himself might not know
what he's doing, that's a separate conversation
if he's not trained enough. But am
I really checking? So interestingly, if you
look in source number 51 in the
Teshuvos Vehanhagos of Rav Sternbuch, so Rav
Sternbuch says 51, this would not work.
It might work for yayin nesech if
you have put in a camera in
an, you know, in an old age
home for a person who has an
aid, it would not work for cholov
yisroel. Meaning if you want to be
if you want to hold like cholov
yisroel and you want to have a
milk that was watched by a Jew,
it doesn't work. So he says the
following: bi'er b'Teshuvos Vehanhagos the following he
says: אם אפשר לסמוך שאכן המשגיח בודק
תמיד כל היום כל התצלומים ממקום החליבה
why not? The guy, the mashgiach is
going to check every single day the
place where they milked וממילא גם האקום
החולב לא מרתע לאורב and he says
nonetheless, נראה שסומך שלא בודקים התצלומים תמיד.
We know, we know, you're not you're
not watching this וכן אני מפקפק אם
המצלמה קולטת כל הנעשה and in addition,
they don't capture every single thing at
every single moment וכן גם ה like
the the everything else stays the same,
they don't capture everything. Ah, okay. So
CRC does use, CRC does use it
for some aspects like the fish market
is under the hashgacha of their cameras
to see that they don't bring in
any non-kosher fish. Right. So the fish
market is under the hashgacha of the
CRC by camera. I'm saying a lot
of kashrus, he's not one second, hold
on a second. Rav Sternbuch isn't saying
he's he's arguing that potentially for something
cholov yisroel he doesn't know that he
would rely on it. That doesn't mean
that other people could disagree with Rav
Sternbuch. Rav Sternbuch's not talking about all
cameras all the time. We don't we
don't allow cameras for yichud issues, for
example, right? Why not? Ah, you there
should be because there you need people.
Ah, that's just sometimes the presence of
somebody is different. To Shai's point, you're
right, you're right. So you know this
is the very famous machine matzah debate,
okay? So the machine matzah debate was
this very thing, right? The, you know,
the first was only machine and come
on. What about sneakers? I don't know,
it was it was before sneakers. Not
the Melamed Leho'il. Rav Nosson of Hanover.
What was the shailos uteshuvos called? Askeil
Teshuvah? Hold on. In an era of
AI cameras that really can see and
process that level of information, does that
change the Yeven Metzulah. No, sorry, that's
the Tach Vat Tat. I'm I'm off.
Ah, whatever. I'll figure it out later.
Yeah, sorry. In an in an era
of AI where we really try so
that's another question. That's a little bit
closer to a real hashgocha protis. You
could pick up little discrepancies. Yes, but
I could also tell you that in
an age of AI, I could mock
up anything that video. So you're talking
about fancy fancy schmancy security cameras. Yeah.
Yeah. Potentially, potentially, and then in real
time. In real time, yeah. Then you
could argue that you're watching. Yeah, so
this was the machine matzah debate. The
machine matzah debate was, hey, we this
is actually going to be much better.
The machine matzah debate actually was not
really about that because it was really
about the introduction of technology within the
world of halacha. Like how modern are
we going to get? That was really
what the debate was about. Oh, we've
covered Zionism tonight and machine matzah. What
a way to wrap up the z'man.
So you're right. Reb Shmuel was saying
he doesn't know that he would hold
of it when it comes to a,
but it also requires if you have
real AI cameras that are going to
ding when something happens maybe, but it
really requires that somebody's going to be
sitting there and actually watching the cameras,
right? So, but that would yotzei v'nichnas
would work. So, if you go to
source 52. So many shuls today have
the non-Jewish help so how does that
work? So he explains the following. It's
pretty simple. He says that wine is
mutar that they clean off the tables
wine. נראה להורות הלכה למעשה במקום שמצוי
שיש נכרי לבית הכנסת, right? The non-Jew
is coming to clean the shul. ויש
מפתחות לנקות גם את המטבח של בית
הכנסת. He's got keys to everything, him
and the president. ויכול להיכנס שם מתי
שרוצה. And he can come in whenever
he wants. ופעמים נשאר בתוכם מקורב בקבוקי
יין פתוחים שאינו מבושל. And there are
times he'll come into a shul, he's
going to clean whenever he wants to
clean, there are wine bottles that are
open. נראה שאין לחוש לאסור. He does
not assur them. Mutarim b'shsiya. Why? B'prat
number one, בית הכנסת תמיד נמצאים שם.
Number one is halevai because you have
yotzei v'nichnas. People in the shul all
the time. And he says v'rav b'arichus
b'he'ara. In the he'ara, they don't quote
it here, but the other part is
that he doesn't want to lose his
job. He starts taking wine, it's not
going to go very well for him.
So therefore we would be he doesn't
want to damage that relationship. That's number
one. If you look in source 53
in the שאלות ותשובות קובץ מבית לוי
the following. So what about somebody who
has an aide? So it depends. This
the shaila comes up very frequently. ובנשאר
בבית חולה או זקן שמרתק למיטה. He's
bedridden. אין זה בגדר שמירה. So if
you have a patient let's say, but
really he's not so conscious. He's there,
but he's not really there. That's not
shemira. Correct. V'yesh lizaheir b'zmanenu. Well, it's
bishul akkum's because right, the caregivers are
cooking meals. But even if the guy
was awake and the goy turned on,
it would be a problem. ויש ליזהר
בזמננו שיש לזקנים ולחולים עובדים נכרים. They
have the non-Jewish workers. Shelo yanich bakbuk.
They should not leave them open. וצריך
לסגור את המקום שאינו יכול לפתחו. You
really have to be careful because that
would not be considered shemira. And therefore,
the last piece is what happens if
I put the wine I know my
maid's coming and whatever and I have
these open bottles or maybe there is
a relative who's in an old age
home and there's wine on the table.
Put it in a place they're not
going to find it. If you know
the place they're not going to find
it, so he says in the Ohel
Yaakov, אם הנכרי אינו יודע כלל שיש
יין ואין לחוש כלל לייחודו. If you
really could put it in a place
where they're not going to find it,
you wouldn't have to worry about it.
באופן המוכח היטב דמסתבר שהנכרי לא ימצאנו,
nireh sheyesh l'hakel that they're not really
going to find it. So again, I
can create a double seal, I could
have cameras. You have to also warn
the goy if there are cameras so
that they're afraid of it. I could
use that combination lock, I could have
one seal potentially b'diavad. I could hide
the wine bottle. And even if none
of those, potentially we would still be
meikel if one needed. Shkoyach.